Charles Emory Smith Collection
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Charles Emory Smith Collection.
undated, 1895-1903.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Unknown.
1 linear foot.
Charles Emory Smith, born 18 February 1842, in Mansfield, CT, was the son of Emory Boutelle and Arvilla Topliff (Royce) Smith. The family relocated to Albany, NY, when Charles was seven and he attended public schools and the Albany Academy, from which he graduated at sixteen. He graduated from Union College in 1861 and went on to become a journalist, diplomat and postmaster-general. He died in Philadelphia, PA, on 19 January 1908.
MSS19880034
Biography
Charles Emory Smith, born 18 February 1842, in Mansfield, CT, was the son of Emory Boutelle and Arvilla Topliff (Royce) Smith. The family relocated to Albany, NY when Charles was seven and he attended public schools and the Albany Academy, from which he graduated at sixteen. He graduated from Union College in 1861 and went on to become a journalist, diplomat and postmaster-general. He died in Philadelphia, PA, on 19 January 1908.
Scope and Content
The Smith Collection contains letters, photographs, printed addresses, and newspaper clippings relating to Mr. Smith. The documents represent only a narrow selection of Smith's activities in the fields of journalism, international diplomacy and his position as postmaster general. Of particular interest are three letters to Smith from President Theodore Roosevelt, including Roosevelt's acceptance of Smith's resignation as Postmaster General of the United States.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut and local history. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919 —Correspondence.
Organizations:
United States. Post Office Dept.; Postal service—United States.
Family Names:
Smith family—Genealogy.
Subjects:
American newspapers—Pennsylvania.; American newspapers—New York (State)—New York.; Diplomatic and consular service, American—Russia.; United States—Foreign relations—Russia.; Russia—Foreign relations—United States.; Mansfield (Conn.)—Resident of.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Photographs.; Genealogies.
Occupations:
Journalist.; Postmaster.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated in September 1988 by Willard Olds.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Collection, undated, 1895-1903
  - Correspondence, Roosevelt to Smith (Box 1)
    - 1902 January 4 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - 1902 December 26 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - 1903 August 18 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Address to the graduating class, Albany Law School, 1900 May 31 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Addresses on the financial question, 1895 April 9 - 10 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Annual report of the Postmaster General, 1898 January 30 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Appomattox day banquet on the Hamilton Club of Chicago: address, 1899 April 10 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Lincoln and Douglass: address of the Postmaster General, 1899 October 7; (4 c.) (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Memorial address on the life and character of James Abram Garfield, 1902 February 27 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - The Silver Question, 1895 April 10; (2 c.) (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - William M'Kinley [sic] memorial address, undated (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Banquet programs, 1898, 1899, 1901 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Peace Jubilee souvenir programme, 1898 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Lebensbeschreibung des Count Orloff, [1903?] (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Bank draft note [copy], 1890 February 26 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Photographs and images, undated, ca. 1860-1900 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Smith Family genealogical information, undated (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - Envelope—Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary, ca. 1890 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Newspapers
    - Brooklyn Daily Eagle, 1899 January 1 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - Daily Republican-Register, 1899 October 7 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - El Paso Daily Herald, 1901 May 6 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - Harper's Weekly, 1901 September 21 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - The Independent, 1899 December 5 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - The Press, 1900 January 20 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - 1900 September 15